YIVO Project. Interviews in the Irving Howe Collection conducted by Bernard Rosenberg. 6036/003
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
YIVO Project. Interviews in the Irving Howe Collection conducted by Bernard Rosenberg.
1968-1968
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
YIVO Institute for Jewish Research
Howe, Irving
Rosenberg, Bernard
6036/003
0.5 cubic feet
0.5 linear ft.
Articles, reprints, pamphlets, correspondence, photographs.
Transcripts of oral history interviews conducted by Bernard Rosenberg for a project of Irving Howe in conjunction with the Yivo Institute for Jewish Research between 1964 and 1968.
5767219
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, August 30, 2011
EAD encoding:
Kathryn Dowgiewicz, January 10, 2013
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States, the ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. In 1995, the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) to form the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE).
Scope and Contents
The collection contains transcripts of oral history interviews with veterans of the Jewish labor movement under the supervision of Professor Irving Howe of the City University of New York. Howe was accumulating material and research in preparation of writing a large volume on immigrant Jews in the U.S., Yiddish culture, and the Jewish labor movement. He had enlisted Professor Bernard Rosenberg, chairman of the sociology department at City College of New York, to conduct the interviews with both leaders and rank and file members of the Jewish labor movement. The project also involved the YIVO Institute for Jewish Research which provided additional support and transcription services. Interviewees include Emil Schlesinger (who provides recollections of his father, former ILGWU president Benjamin Schlesinger)and Israel Breslow, but many of the transcripts are in Yiddish.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 6036/002: YIVO Archives. Interviews in Amerikaner Yiddishe Geschichte Bel- Pe.
Jewish labor unions; Breslow, Israel.; Deutchman, Max.; Fenster, Bernard.; Glass, Louis.; Halpern, Gershon.; Halpern, Pearl.; Haskel, Hannah.; Haskel, Max.; Held, Adolph.; Hershovitz, Abe.; Kazin, Abraham.; Kreindler, Charles.; Novick, Paul.; Painkin, Louis.; Scherer, Abraham.; Schlesinger, Emil.; Schoenholtz, Isidore.; Shapiro, Feigel.; Weiss, Flora.; Wisotsky, Isidore.; Zierlin, Abe.; Yivo Institute for Jewish Research; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5767219
- Abe Hershovitz, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  #2 R.I. 14. Interviewed by YIVO Institute at the Amalgamated Clothing Workers Union on May 26, 1964. Typed Yiddish. 33 pages.
- Pearl and Gershon Halpern, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  #2 R.I. 15. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on November 11, 1965. Typed Yiddish. 32 pages and 6 pages.
- Emil Schlesinger, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  #2 R.I. 16. Interviewed by YIVO Institute on May 8 and 9, 1968. 41 pages.
- Flora Weiss, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  #2 R.I. 17. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on June 15, 1964. Typed Yiddish. 45 pages.
- Bernard Fenster, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  #2 R.I. 18. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on December 6, 1963. Typed Yiddish. 20 pages.
- Louis Glass [Folder 1 of 2], 1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  #2 R.I. 19. Interviewed by YIVO Institute on November 4, 1963. Typed Yiddish. 59 pages.
- Louis Glass [Folder 2 of 2], 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Abe Zierlin, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  #2 R.I. 20. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on May 4, 1964. Typed Yiddish. 16 pages.
- Abraham Scherer, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  #2 R.I. 21. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on November 23, 1963. Typed Yiddish. 16 pages.
- Isidore Schoenholtz, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  #2 R.I. 22. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on May 16, 1964. Typed Yiddish. 33 pages.
- Charles Kreindler, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  #2 R.I. 23. Interviewed by YIVO Institute on August 2, 1965. 11 pages.
- Hannah Haskel (Mrs. Charles Kreindler), 1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  #2 R.I. 24. Interviewed by YIVO Institute on March 16, 1965. 25 pages.
- Max Haskel, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  #2 R.I. 25. Interviewed by YIVO Institute, circa 1964-1965. Typed Yiddish. 4 pages.
- Feigel Shapiro, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  #2 R.I. 26. Interviewed by YIVO Institute on Auguts 6, 1964. Includes typed Yiddish. 32 pages.
- Max Deutchman, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  #2 R.I. 27. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on February 3 and 7, 1964. Typed Yiddish. 31 pages.
- Abraham Kazin, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  #3 R.I. 1. Interviewed by Bernard Rosenberg. 23 pages.
- Isidore Wisotsky, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  #3 R.I. 2. Interviewed by Bernard Rosenberg. 31 pages.
- Paul Novick, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  #3 R.I. 3. Interviewed by Bernard Rosenberg. 22 pages.
- Adolph Held, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  #3 R.I. 4. Interviewed by Bernard Rosenberg. 21 pages.
- Pearl Halpern, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  #3 R.I. 5. Interviewed by Bernard Rosenberg. 26 pages.
- Louis Painkin, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  #3 R.I. 6. Interviewed by Bernard Rosenberg. 48 pages.
- Israel Breslow, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  #3 R.I. 7. Interviewed by Bernard Rosenberg. 31 pages.
- Abe Zierlin and wife, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  #3 R.I. 8. Interviewed by Bernard Rosenberg. 18 pages.